PERVAIZ AHMED

House No. 752, Street 19, Sector I-8/2 Islamabad, Pakistan Cell: +92-303-5535543 – Email: pervaiz87@gmail.com Skype: pervaizhunzai

PROFILE

An accomplished Rural Development Specialist and a social entrepreneur with over 25 years of experience in designing and managing multi-donor funded social/rural development programs in Pakistan. With a deep knowledge of social and rural development sector in Pakistan and Central Asia, strong technical competencies in conceptualizing/developing innovative **community driven programs**, excellent management and leadership skills, Mr. Ahmed is highly dependable and reliable professional. He led the rural development portfolio of Aga Khan Foundation (AKF) in Pakistan from 2002-2011, and has longstanding experience in design, implementation, **monitoring and evaluation** of rural development programs, Since January 2012, Mr. Ahmed's consulting practice has focused on impact **evaluation** and project design in the above fields for national and international NGOs and development agencies. Mr. Ahmed holds a M.Sc. (Animal Science) from the University of Reading UK.

FUNCTIONAL SKILLS:

Multi-stakeholder processes, **social mobilization** for sustainable livelihoods and **community driven education system**, workshop and training facilitation, monitoring, evaluation and research, report writing, interpersonal and team building skills; mentoring, multi-tasking, ability to work under pressure and in a multi cultural environment.

KEY EXPERTISE

- <u>Program Design:</u> strategic planning, Result Based Management, project concept note and proposal writing, agriculture and rural development programming.
- <u>Program Management:</u> planning, monitoring and reporting, and evaluation of donor funded rural development projects.
- <u>Institutional and Social Development:</u> gender analysis, social mobilization, needs assessment, facilitation of workshops, technical assistance and capacity building of partner organizations and grassroots organizations.
- <u>Humanitarian Assistance and DRM</u>: management of relief, early recovery and rehabilitation projects and community based disaster risk reduction.
- <u>Food Security, Agriculture and Livelihoods:</u> small scale dairy development, agriculture and livestock value chain development and agri-business development.
- <u>Private Sector Development:</u> Market Development and micro and small enterprise development.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Freelance Development Consultant, Islamabad, Pakistan

Jan 2012 - Present

Consultancy Assignments Undertaken to Date

February-March 2014: Research Consultant

Reviewed Economic Empowerment of Women: Assessment of Dynamics and Factors Inhibiting Women's Self-employment in Gilgit-Baltistan and Chitral (GBC) district of KPK for AKRSP, Pakistan. The main purpose of this assignment was a desk research to review the factors limiting women's self-employment in GBC.

December 2013 - Jan 2014: Evaluation Consultant

Designed and conducted end evaluation of EC funded "Support to Fruit Nursery Tree Industry in Afghanistan" Project for MADERA in Afghanistan. The main purpose of this project was to develop perennial fruit industry in Afghanistan. As part of the evaluation process, travelled across Afghanistan to Nangarhar, Laghman, Kunar, Herat and Kandhar provinces for data collection besides holding meetings with the field staff of the five implementing partners and other key stakeholders as part of the consortium led by MADERA.

November/December 2013: Consultant

Design and execution of Partners' Conference on "Development of Renewable Energy Resources in Gilgit-Baltistan". Developed a concept note on "Promotion of Renewable Energy for Sustainable Economic Growth in GB" for Government of Gilgit-Baltistan. The two assignments entailed working closely with the Water and Power Department (WAPD) of GB and other key stakeholders within and outside GB. The client was s Sustainable Solutions (Pvt.) Ltd. Pakistan

August/September 2013, Evaluation Team Leader:

Led the team of three consultants to undertake the End of Project Evaluation of "Building Resilience through Community Based Disaster Risk Management (CBDRM) in the Sindh Province" for Rural Support Programs Network (RSPN), Pakistan. Funded by USAID, the objectives of TAHAFUZ Project were: To develop the capacity of the community in disaster preparedness, management and mitigation; b) to develop the hazard risk reduction plans, policies and curriculum; and c) to increase preparedness of local community from proposed hydrological activities (floods and cyclones). This End of Project Evaluation report provided an assessment of the TAHAFUZ Project's relevance, efficiency, and effectiveness as per the evaluation TOR.

March/April 2013, Evaluation Consultant:

Together with Cynosure Consulting Firm, Conducted Impact Evaluation of the Livelihood Component of "Integrated Afghan Refugees Assistance Program in

Baluchistan for Mercy Corps Pakistan". Funded by US Embassy, this project was implemented by Mercy Corps to enhance the economic opportunities for Afghan Refugees with an aim to facilitate their repatriation to Afghanistan. The project has directly benefited over 3000 men and women by enhancing their technical and vocational skills to enhance their employability.

December, 2012, Evaluation Team Leader:

Design and conduct of End of Project Evaluation of "Preservation and Promotion of Arts and Cultural Heritage in KPK" for the Royal Norwegian Embassy, Islamabad. The Project was implemented by Baacha Khan Trust for Education Foundation (BKTEF) in their 14 schools across KPK. The main purpose of this evaluation was to assess Project design, effectiveness, efficiency, impact and sustainability of the project interventions which included curriculum of culture education and its contribution to revival of culture heritage as potent force to deal with extremism.

July/Aug 2012, Project Development Consultant:

Developed a winning funding proposal for Sustainable Solutions (Pvt.) Limited and secured funding for "Raising People's Voice for Power Sector Reforms in Gilgit-Baltistan Project" under USAID supported Citizen's Voice Project. Led the process of Project Implementation Plan (PIP) and M&E system besides recruitment of project staff and their orientation.

June/July 2012, Monitoring and Reporting Consultant:

Together with Sustainable Solutions (Pvt.) Ltd. conducted annual monitoring of USAID funded "Dairy and Rural Development Foundation (DRDF) Project for Dairy Development in Punjab Province" and prepared the first annual report covering the achievements, challenges, lessons learnt and the way forward.

May/June 2012, Evaluation Consultant:

Design and conduct of End of Project Evaluation of "Inclusive Development through Mainstreaming Persons With Disabilities in the Process of Social Mobilization in District Jehlum Punjab" for Sightsavers International. Civil Society Human and Institutional Development Program (CHIP) has implemented this project with the technical assistance of Special Talent Exchange Program (STEP). The purpose of this project is to promote inclusion of Persons with Disabilities in local development.

January/Feb 2012, Impact Evaluation Consultant:

Together with Cynosure Consulting Firm, Conducted Impact Assessment of "Enhancing Food Security and Resilience of Small and Vulnerable Farmers Project in Dadu and Sanghar districts in Sindh Province and Musa Khel district in Baluchistan" for Oxfam GB. Funded by EC, this project was implemented by Sindh Agriculture and Forestry Workers Coordination Organisation (SAFWCO) in Sindh and by BEEJ in Musa Khel.

December/Jan 2012, Evaluation Consultant:

Design and conduct of end of project evaluation of "Addressing Poverty and Environment Nexus in Northern Pakistan" for Project Procurement International / Aga Khan Foundation (Pakistan). This project was implemented by Aga Khan Planning and Building Service, Pakistan under its Building and Construction Improvement Program to promote improved housing and energy efficient products in the two valleys in Chitral to improve their living conditions.

STAFF / PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS:

Aga Khan Foundation (Pakistan) May 2002 – Aug 2011 Programme Manager, Rural Development – Islamabad, Pakistan

Provided leadership for significant growth of rural development (RD) portfolio through new project development and reosurce mobilization. Provision of technical guidance and robust monitoring enabled AKDN partners to achieve the desired outcomes. Led the strategic development of RD, humanitarian response and DRM programs of AKF for Pakistan. Successfully managed AKF's relations with international donors and other partners. Developed partnerships with ADB and World Bank on Gilgit-Baltistan's economic potential through research effort. Co-conceptualized the AKDN's Multi-Input Area Development Programme for Pakistan including cross-border community-driven small infrastructure projects as part of regional development strategy for Afghanistan, Pakistan and Tajikistan.

Aga Khan Education Service, Pakistan (AKES,P) Feb 2001– March 2002 Senior Community Development Trainer – Gilgit Pakistan

In this role, successfully supported: capacity building of AKES,P in community development approaches focusing on social mobilization to enhance community participation in promoting female education in under-developed areas of GB. Main contribution was designing tailor-made training program for AKES,P's mid management cadre and local education committees for capacity-building in community driven education program and improved school management and fund mobilization for female education. Contributed to strategic development of AKES,P's community development program for EC funding proposal. Built the capacity of education managers in qualitative research methods and provided strategic support in setting up M&E Unit within AKES.P.

Aga Khan Rural Support Programme (AKRSP), Nov 1999 – Jan 2001 Manager, Social Development and Training, Gilgit Pakistan

With renewed organizational focus on poverty and equity, implemented regional social development strategy in Gilgit region. Conducted a process review of the community-based poverty pilot projects and documented the lessons learned for replication in other program regions. Facilitated several workshops and meetings for the regional professional staff on key social development issues including **social mobilization**, **institutional development and capacity building of community institutions** in local planning and management of community driven projects. Contributed to strategic

development of AKRSP's training program and strengthened training delivery capacity of AKRSP.

AKRSP March 1997 – Oct 1999

Manager, MER/Gender and Development, Gilgit - Pakistan

Led the revitalization process of the MER unit and developed a capacity building plan to operationalize the Log frame-based progress reporting. Developed the **LFA-based reporting system** in consultation with DFID Advisor. Trained field based staff on the results- based reporting templates and qualitative research. Contributed to staff capacity development program on M&E in collaboration with University of East Anglia, UK. As a result, 13 research studies were produced including four impact studies. Contributed to Gender and Development strategy and implementation of action plan to ensure gender equality in development outcomes.

AKRSP April 1995 – Feb 1997

Manager, Field Operations Sub-district Gilgit - Pakistan

Mobilized over **200 Village and Women's Organisations** for planning and implementation of local development projects including small community driven productive infrastructure projects; credit and savings; and livelihood interventions in one of the most **socially and geographically challenging areas** of Pakistan. Built the capacity of community institutions for improved planning and management of community driven projects and common property resources. Promoted microenterprises and better management of micro-credit operations. Effectively managed the multi-disciplinary team of professionals and their mentoring.

AKRSP Jan 1989 – Marc 19995

Manager, Livestock Development, Skardu and Gilgit - Pakistan

Designed, implemented and monitored interventions to increase livestock productivity and income of small farmers. Successfully introduced new cattle breeds, increased farmers knowledge in livestock management and disease control through vaccination. Introduced private livestock extension services and sustainable supply of inputs in GB region. Designed and implemented training courses for rural women in poultry semi-commercial poultry rearing to contribute to their economic empowerment.

AKRSP Jan 1987-Dec 1989

Project Office, Livestock Development, Gilgit - Pakistan

Major contribution was in improving livestock productivity through disease control, feed and breed improvement. Promoted home based poultry and dairy production for increased household income.

EDUCATION:

University of Reading, UK, M.Sc. (Animal Science) **1994** University of Agriculture Faisalabad, Pakistan, DVM, 1986

TRAINING COURSES WORKSHOPS AND CONFERENCES ATTENDED:

Participated in several international professional training courses in rural / social development, monitoring, and evaluation from Holland and UK. In addition, attended the workshops and conferences organized by AKF on rural development including NRM, market development, agriculture value chain development in Switzerland, India, Dubai, Dushanbe, Dhaka and Glasgow, UK. Conducted study tour to Bangladesh, Tajikistan, East Africa on micro-finance, Early Childhood Development, Community Based Savings Groups, livelihoods and community based education system.

LANGUAGES:

English (Excellent), Urdu (Excellent), Punjabi (Good), Pushtu (very basic), Persian/Dari (very basic) and speak most of the regional dialects of Gilgit Baltistan Region including Brushisky, Shina and Khuwar.

PERSONAL HISTORY:

Born on Dec 13, 1959 an Pakistan national